<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-18T11:33:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Collin Ching</title><subtitle>Source code for my blog</subtitle><author><name>Collin Ching</name><email>collindching@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">My habits for 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/habits-for-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My habits for 2021" /><published>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/habits-for-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/habits-for-2021/">&lt;p&gt;With Covid-19, the shift to remote work and distanced socializing, and the climax of radicalized politics, 2020 has been such an eventful year. I think the world has learned many lessons about work, social discourse, and politics, and that we will see lasting, positive change in these landscapes moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 has also been an eventful year at a personal level. In January, I traveled to India, where I met people who were different from me on paper, but similar to me in temperament, values, and personal drive. In February, I started my first data science role, where I worked at a FANG company and proved myself as a valuable and dependable resource. I experienced life in San Jose and San Francisco. I started reading and picked up journaling, and took care of a health issue – gout – that had been problematic for years. And then in December, I left my first data science role and started my second data science role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud of what I’ve accomplished in 2020. But I want to take a moment to examine what I didn’t accomplish last year and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/goals-2020.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these goals, the only one I did was build a personal website. I aimed for 75% success, but achieved 25%. I have three hypotheses as to why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my goals were too ambitious because I underestimated the amount of stress/time that my data science job demanded of me. Last spring, many nights saw me working furiously and anxiously to finish deliverables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I overestimated my motivation throughout the working week to accomplish these longer-term goals. But the problem here may have been systematic: my guess is that while I set lofty goals, I didn’t give myself enough positive and incremental feedback to stay motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, I didn’t hold myself accountable to the processes that lead to goal attainment—I didn’t track my productive habits. I only tracked whether or not I had reached my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use an example, Cal Newport, author of Deep Work, tracks the hours he spends in a deep work state. By focusing on this, instead of whether or not he completes his task, he reframes his approach to productivity in two ways. First, he optimizes for the processes that lead to success. And second, he focuses on what he can objectively accomplish in the allotted time (spend 1 hour doing deep work) instead of working on an unpredictable goal (finishing a presentation with 1 hour of work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this year, I’m going to try something new. Instead of tracking my goals, I’m going to track my habits – if I can maintain these good habits, the results should follow. I’ll continue to keep goals, but by focusing on the process of achieving, I can be more accountable for my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daily-habits&quot;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 2021 habits are centered around health, mental clarity, and personal development. To keep myself accountable to them, I’ve set up a database in Notion that tracks either (a) if I’ve done an activity, or  (b) how long I’ve spent on an activity. By the end of the day, I’ll build out some visualizations to reflect on how I’ve done with my habits. I’ve ordered them based on the order in the day in which I’ll do them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;morning-habits&quot;&gt;Morning habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complete all these rituals, I need to wake up two hours priod to starting the workday, which also means sleeping early enough to get &amp;gt;8 hours of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eating oatmeal:&lt;/strong&gt; A morning ritual to anchor my nutrition and serve as a reminder to eat healthy foods&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journaling:&lt;/strong&gt; A 15-minute session each morning set aside for reflection, processing, and setting intentions and priorities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning hour:&lt;/strong&gt; An hour dedicated to personal development – primarily in learning data science/investing or in building projects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evening-habits&quot;&gt;Evening habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exercising:&lt;/strong&gt; A 30-minute session immediately following the end of the workday, to cue the transition to the second half of my day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing:&lt;/strong&gt; A 20-minute session for expounding on the things I’m learning, working on, or thinking about for my personal blog – this is an opportunity to dive deeply, process thoughts, develop informed opinions, and improve my communication&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Chinese:&lt;/strong&gt; A 15-minute session to practice vocabulary via Anki or a 30-minute session to speak with a teacher on iTalki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nighttime-habits&quot;&gt;Nighttime habits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading:&lt;/strong&gt; Pre-bed routine as a way to unwind and expand my worldview – this is an opportunity to learn about anything that I find interesting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;visions-for-the-end-of-2021&quot;&gt;Visions for the end of 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am healthier, happier, and wiser by December, 2021 will have been a success. There are four buckets that I’d like to especially keep a tally on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although 2020 was a year of health setbacks for me. I’ve learned a hard lesson that health is the single most important asset a person has. I want to look back on the year and feel that I’ve invested in my body, and left it in better shape than the previous year. The hope is that future Collin will be in good health and feel excited that he’s able to do, thanks to the investments of past Collin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mental-clarity&quot;&gt;Mental clarity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to reclaim my ability to do deep work, and be able to focus deeply, think clearly and creatively, and work calmly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to become a great data scientist, and feel confident in my ability to solve complex problems. By the end of the year, I want to prove that I am thoughtful, technical, and creative – and demonstrate this by example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to invest in my problem solving skills and technical skills (coding + data) to support my goals as a data scientist, and to to set myself with a foundational skillset for future entrepreneurial pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chinese&quot;&gt;Chinese&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reward myself for learning Chinese, I plan to visit China in fall of 2021, Covid pending. The hope is that I’ll be able to read menus, interact with locals, and experience the country deeply. Ultimately, I’d like to make the most of reconnecting with my cultural heritage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Collin Ching</name><email>collindching@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Committing to consistency in health and personal development</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep work principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/doing-deep-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep work principles" /><published>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/doing-deep-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/doing-deep-work/">&lt;p&gt;Deep work refers to the set of professional activities that you accomplish in a state of intense, undistracted focus. The ability to consistently accomplish deep work is important because it allows you to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn things quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Master difficult skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solve meaningful and interesting problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Become a valuable asset in today’s economy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Derive satisfaction from crafting quality work and attaining flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But deep work is not something that comes easily; it requires effective routines, concentration training, and management of shallow work to maintain the habit. Cal Newport shares &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.doist.com/deep-work/&quot;&gt;four guiding principles&lt;/a&gt; principles that help cultivate a deep work habit in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calnewport.com/books/deep-work/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I’ve reframed for use in my own life as a lifelong learner and problem solver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build deep work routines&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use a scheduling method&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use depth rituals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Execute like a business&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Commit to ending your work day&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nurture your focus&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Limit context switching&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use social media and phones deliberately&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schedule quality breaks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Practice mindfulness&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tame your shallow work&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schedule every minute of your day&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use a fixed productivity schedule&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Communicate efficiently&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal with this page is to provide a gain so that you can maintain a maintain a deep work habit and reap the rewards of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-deep-work-routines&quot;&gt;Build deep work routines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep work is difficult, and willpower alone isn’t enough to consistently work deeply. Leverage rituals and strategies that lower the barriers to getting work done. These were the select strategies I found most helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-scheduling-method&quot;&gt;Use a scheduling method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine when you accomplish your deep work, Cal Newport prescribes four main scheduling philosophies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monastic:&lt;/strong&gt; A hermetic approach to deep work which involves retreating from society for long stretches of time to remain in an extreme state of deep work. Suitable for people who don’t have regular obligations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bimodal:&lt;/strong&gt; Schedule medium-length periods of deep work, punctuated by equal-length periods in which shallow work and other obligations can be taken care of.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rhythmic:&lt;/strong&gt; Schedule a set daily time to work deeply. While the state of focus achieved with rhythmic scheduling isn’t as intense as monastic or bimodal scheduling, rhythmic scheduling is the most suitable for people who work in office jobs. This, in addition to journalistic scheduling, is the approach to deep work scheduling that I ascribe to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journalistic:&lt;/strong&gt; Schedule deep work sessions whenever there is available free time. Suitable for people with busy and changing schedules. This requires significant planning to block out deep work periods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My approach to deep work scheduling is both rhythmic and journalistic. I wake up regularly around 7am, so that I get a daily deep work session from 7:30 - 9am. This is my most effective time of day, and it is protected time to invest in myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work begins at 9am, at which point I transition to journalistic scheduling, with work sessions planned ad-hoc around the workday’s meetins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I schedule my deep work before the day has started to eliminate on-the-spot decision making. Having a prepared plan makes it more likely that I will accomplish the deep work session that I previously committed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-depth-rituals&quot;&gt;Use depth rituals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A depth ritual is a ritual that you use to transition into a state of deep focus more seamlessly and work more effectively. These rituals do so by priming you for deep work, keeping you focused, and limiting working distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my depth routine, at minimum I will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set phone to &lt;em&gt;Do Not Disturb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start timer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When engaging in an intense deep work session, I will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare a thermos of water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write down:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Session goal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Start and end time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Subtasks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set phone to &lt;em&gt;Do Not Disturb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start timer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is to set focus boundaries, record a specific and actionable goal, and limit context switching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;execute-like-a-business&quot;&gt;Execute like a business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newport also recommends approaching work like you would approach running a business. He draws four analogies from a business setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on your top priorities:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your priorities focused, identify a small number of ambitious outcomes to pursue with your deep work hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Act on lead meaures:&lt;/strong&gt; Focus on optimizing metrics that track actions that drive your success (track deep work hours).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep a scoreboard of your deep work time:&lt;/strong&gt; To serve as a visual reminder of your personal and professional productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a cadence of accountability:&lt;/strong&gt; Do a weekly review of your deep work sessions to analyze what went well and what didn’t, and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commit-to-ending-your-work-day&quot;&gt;Commit to ending your work day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shut off your work at a regular time daily. After this time, don’t think about work. This commitment will improve your working efficiency, problem solving capacity, and quality of life, based on the following observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Downtime is an opportunity to apply your subconscious, diffused processing to solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rest and relaxation recharges the energy you need to work deeply (&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your deep work ability declines later in the day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ending your work day gives you time to develop your personal interests, and grow outside of work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this, commit to a shutdown ritual at a specific time. My 6pm ritual involves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recording what I’ve done for the day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing a brief plan for my remaining work, to be executed the next day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Closing my laptop and organizing my desk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay to extend your workday if you need more time. The key point is not the timing, but the commitment to turning work off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nurture-your-focus&quot;&gt;Nurture your focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of your focus &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nwtutoring.com/2019/06/03/focus-is-a-muscle/&quot;&gt;as a muscle&lt;/a&gt; that becomes stronger with training and performs optimally under certain conditions. If neglected and constantly fed low-quality distraction, your focus will atrophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a long-term commitment to mental training, and follow best practices to train your brain and improve your ability to produce rare and valuable work. Some strategies that can help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;limit-context-switching&quot;&gt;Limit context switching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context switching imposes cognitive load on the brain through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200130-the-life-hack-to-reduce-admin-and-carve-out-downtime&quot;&gt;attention residue&lt;/a&gt;. Whenever you switch tasks, a portion of your brain’s attention will still be processing the previous task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You lose a little bit of performance every time you switch task contexts, however brief, which is why even a quick glance at social media leads to significance reductions in work performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When performing deep work, commit to your task context for the duration of your session.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-social-media-and-phones-deliberately&quot;&gt;Use social media and phones deliberately&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and smartphones &lt;a href=&quot;https://now.northropgrumman.com/this-is-your-brain-on-instagram-effects-of-social-media-on-the-brain/#:~:text=According%20to%20an%20article%20by,%E2%80%A6%20and%20now%2C%20social%20media.&quot;&gt;hijack&lt;/a&gt; the brain’s reward system and make it difficult for us to control our actions and impulses. It’s important to wrest control of your brain away from these technologies, and train yourself to work towards long-term rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be thoughtful about how often you check social media and other websites.&lt;/strong&gt; As you train yourself to fight internet impulses, you’ll improve your ability to fight internet distractions and focus on tasks that benefit your long-term goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;schedule-quality-breaks&quot;&gt;Schedule quality breaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more effectively you rest, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/acp.3334&quot;&gt;better equipped&lt;/a&gt; you are to focus in your next session. Additionally, scheduling breaks to look forward to can you help you stay motivated during a deep work session. Taking high quality breaks will improve your quality of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the most out of your breaks, (1) schedule when you’ll take your breaks, and (2) plan what activity you’ll do during your breaks. This ensures (a) optimal break timing and (b) optimal break quality. Do &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onlineschools.org/science-of-study-breaks/&quot;&gt;not&lt;/a&gt; use a screen during your break:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/regular-exercise-changes-brain-improve-memory-thinking-skills-201404097110&quot;&gt;Move&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Walk&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stretch&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Workout&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attention_restoration_theory&quot;&gt;Change your scenery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/03/150320091315.htm&quot;&gt;Nap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mindfulness activity
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Meditation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chores&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draw&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socialize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practice-mindfulness&quot;&gt;Practice mindfulness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness simply refers to being present in the moment. Oftentimes, this refers to meditation, but it describes any activity in which you’re completely, fully engaged. &lt;strong&gt;These activities are extremely helpful for honing your focus.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness activities include reading, cooking, and walking. Try to prioritize these activities in your downtime, and treat them as opportunities to be mindful of the present, and enjoy simple pleasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tame-your-shallow-work&quot;&gt;Tame your shallow work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep work is valuable and should not be ignored, but shallow work is also necessary. Make it your goal to take care of your shallow work efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;schedule-every-minute-of-your-day&quot;&gt;Schedule every minute of your day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise forces you to think about how you want your time to be spent. One way is to draw out your schedule in 15-minute blocks. I use a time blocking method that Cal Newport describes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2013/12/21/deep-habits-the-importance-of-planning-every-minute-of-your-work-day/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, give yourself flexibility to change your schedule as things pop up throughout the day. But make sure to keep track of how your time actually gets used. Accounting for your time allows you to be more deliberate with deep work, shallow work, breaks, and transition time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-a-fixed-productivity-schedule&quot;&gt;Use a fixed productivity schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By giving yourself a fixed amount of time to complete your work obligations, you become better at trimming the fat around your work schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should follow is that you guard your time better and learn to say no to nonessential obligations, giving you more time to dedicate to essential work activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communicate-efficiently&quot;&gt;Communicate efficiently&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the amount of back-and-forth effort that gets used in email communications, send the message that brings your conversation to a logical conclusion in the least number of emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The additional effort in crafting a succint message is worth the effort in terms of long-run conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-striving&quot;&gt;Keep striving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a good deep work habit isn’t easy. Think of it as a process, and keep striving for growth and improvement. To borrrow from Michelle Obama, “reach continuously toward a better self.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strive for improvement. Reflect on what you can do better. And resolve to push through obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plan well, make adjustments, and be gentle with yourself. Good results will follow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Collin Ching</name><email>collindching@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Strategies for working effectively, from Cal Newport's _Deep Work_</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My career priorities (October 2020)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/career-priorities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My career priorities (October 2020)" /><published>2020-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/career-priorities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/career-priorities/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been creeping on Blind lately, an app where software engineers and data scientists share their compensation packages from major tech companies. And while it is fun to see what my peers earn, scrolling through posts has also been stressful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I paid enough? Can I get paid more? My life would be so much better if I had x more dollars. How do I raise my salary to y dollars? What company, which skills, what projects should I focus on to get more money?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably spent an entire week thinking solely about making more money, until it occurred to me that I hadn’t assessed how important salary was to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How important is money to me right now? What do I want out of my next job? What problems am I interested in solving? What do I want from life, in general?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reflected on the questions above and realized that, while compensation was a top priority for people posting on Blind, skill development has been a higher short-term priority for me. Comparing myself to others on the basis on compensation reduced my worth to a single number that didn’t do my efforts jutstice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to the point of this post: it’s important to evaluate and record your career priorities and reasons for having them. Doing so forces you to consider what matters to you thoughtfully. And in times of doubt, having a record of your priorities can be helpful reminder to stick to your plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, here are my priorities as of October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-master-data-science-skills&quot;&gt;1. Master data science skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently prioritizing skill mastery over career advancement. Given the option to either grow my skills or receive a salary bump, I’m will forego a short-term salary increase if it means quicker growth as a data professional. In the mid-term and long-term, good career advancement opportunities should follow as a lagging measure of skill mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My number 1 priority is to &lt;strong&gt;master technical skills&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;critical thinking&lt;/strong&gt; necessary to do great data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On technical skill development, I’m interested in learning statistical, ML, or programming concepts as they apply to driving high-impact business decisions or products. I have a lot on my learning wishlist, but topics that I want to tackle with greater depth are SQL, basics of data engineering, modeling techniques and ML algorithms, methods of model deployment, experimentation methods, and causal inference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the softer side, I want to hone the critical thinking necessary to identifying an important business problem, exploring that problem’s business/data context rigorously, and building an actionable solution. This is more important than mastering any technical skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I pursue this goal I will focus on deliberate and direct practice. My primary learning processes will be building, drilling, and writing. I intend to reinforce anything I learn passively (via reading, coursework) through active learning. While this may lead to slower progress and greater effort on my end, I believe this will be most effective for long-term growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-build-great-learning-and-working-habits&quot;&gt;2. Build great learning and working habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since learning will be crucial for my personal and career development, I am convinced that optimizing my learning habits would pay huge dividends. In studying the art of learning, my goal is to collect strategies that can lead to a lifetime of more efficient and effective learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I’ll be studying recurring behaviors that top performers use to achieve their goals, writing down their principles and habits, and applying and refining a strategy that works best for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My process for accomplishing this goal will be reading and summarizing books about learning, capturing the key strategies on my personal blog, and then keeping myself accountable to the habits that are most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very excited about this priority and how it will affect my life outside of just work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-learn-how-the-world-operates&quot;&gt;3. Learn how the world operates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstractly, I’d like to learn how the world works and how people operate both as individuals and as members of systems. Reading and reflecting on these questions will hopefully help me discover questions that matter to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a more concrete goal, I’d like to accumulate a collection of mental models that I can refer to about how and why things happen, and tie these back into my life in some way. Maybe some of these can be a basis for a future project or career move in data science, and help me improve either my life or someone else’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a habit, I’ll aim to read a diverse range of non-fiction subjects – economics, psychology, philosophy, history, biographies/memoirs, science – and amass a centralized collection of written notes. This will be the foundation for connecting ideas between disciplines and developing new mental models.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Collin Ching</name><email>collindching@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Why scrolling Blind is dangerous, and why setting personal goals is important</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to program and debug more effectively as a data scientist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming-lessons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to program and debug more effectively as a data scientist" /><published>2020-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming-lessons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming-lessons/">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I delivered my first software package, designed to automate some time-intensive calculations that are critical to my team’s data workflow. The process included more debug cycles than I care to admit, partly because of growing code complexity and evolving requirements, and partly because I could have planned and executed more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some reflection, here are some key lessons from that experience, which can help you write software more effectively as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-map-out-your-software-design&quot;&gt;1. Map out your software design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my project, I dove into coding with limited upfront planning, thinking that the exact details of my software design would become clearer as I coded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my code became more complex, I started losing track of how all my functions fit together. When requirements changed, I had to reinvest time into understanding my code to make desired modifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding this pitfall takes relatively little effort. Have a simple, but clear picture of what your software does at a high-level, whether you draw out a diagram or take notes on your software’s design and functions. Keeping a sketch with pen-and-paper and boxes and arrows would suffice. I personally wrote bullets on a working document that I could constantly modify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several advantages of keeping a design map. For one, documenting your software design will give you a clearer idea of how all your code pieces fit together. Verbalizing the logic of your data manipulations can help you sense check that your logic will give you your intended result. And of course, having a clear reference becomes extremely handy when you need to make bigger changes to the design of your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-invest-in-file-organization&quot;&gt;2. Invest in file organization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between multiple scripts and Excel files, I grossly underestimated the number of files that I would be navigating throughout my project. When my ad-hoc file naming system eventually failed, I found myself re-writing several functions because I couldn’t find the original files in which I’d written them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing in your organization will inevitably reduce stress down the line, and improve long-term efficiency. Before starting a project, it’s helpful to invest some upfront effort to define a clear, maintainable file organization and naming system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some basics guidelines would be to have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A separate folder for each project you’re working on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A folder for each of your respective file categories (i.e. scripts, data, outputs, QA, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A consistent naming convention for code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A consistent naming convention for your data files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, I found it helpful to use version tags and date tags on code and data files (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;v2-file-2020-08-03&lt;/code&gt;), to make it easier to navigate by chronology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-validate-each-code-unit&quot;&gt;3. Validate each code unit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debugging was the most painful part of my programming project by far. This pain often stemmed narrowing down the location of bugs. One lesson I learned was to validate regularly at each transformation step, to ensure that any data processing result had values and dimensions I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed me to catch unexpected behavior early on, and allowed me to be confident about data at each step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple basic checks that I regularly used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking number of rows before and after joining two data frames&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking that sums of variables match up before and after processing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checking for missing values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To increase efficiency and repeat keystrokes, I would think about ways to automate validation, either through by creating simple validation functions or Excel templates. For me, time invested in automating validation easily paid itself off tenfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-debug-methodically&quot;&gt;4. Debug methodically&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When errors arise, debugging by following your instincts can sometimes pay off. But without a plan, this approach can be arbitrary and frustrating. In the long-term, following a methodical debugging procedure is a more effective strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a system in which you narrow down sources of error and document attempted solutions can help you more effectively circle in on a solution. Moreover, this keeps stress at bay, allowing you to focus on debugging with an organized and calm mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a high-level, I think a system should involve understanding the error message, developing context around the bug, and testing and documenting solutions in an organized fashion. In this system, you get more control over your debugging process, a reference document for future debugging cycles, and significant reduction in stress in exchange for a small additional investment in time and effort. The procedure that I’ve been using is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If there is an error message, read it carefully and look it up; if not, describe the unexpected behavior in writing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrow down the location of the offending code by inserting manual tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you’ve identified where the error occurs, check the structure, format, and values of the data entering your offending code – usually this will lead to a solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fix, re-run, evaluate, document&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the error persists, research the error further and test again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the error persists, ask for debugging help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While your system might be different, I think the core principles will be the same: understand your error, locate the bug, investigate obvious sources of error, and test and document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-document-bugs-and-solutions&quot;&gt;5. Document bugs and solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course of my project, I caught myself debugging the same problem several times, which was an inefficient use of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid solving the same problem twice, I started maintaining a document of bugs that I ran into, along with their solutions. This reference also has a preventative benefit, allowing me to keep track of common bugs and avoid making those mistakes in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest keeping your solution document simple; you can keep track of each error you face in a spreadsheet – mine only has four columns: error, context, solution, and notes for next time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Collin Ching</name><email>collindching@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Lessons from my first data science software project</summary></entry></feed>